so
what did we say we're going to talk
about sensuality and safety
sensuality and safety
specifically sensuality what was
what was the specific thing
do you have more specific the domain the
extent so the people think about it as in
so the people think about it as in
clarified their thinking on it once they
knew that that's what we're going to
talk about
well the first thing that you'd want to
clarify is when you say the extent of
the sensual domain
do you mean
the extent of
extent of
the range of
the physical senses or the extents of
like the principle of sensuality
uh the sensuality
the principle
yeah okay what would the sense organs
without the principle of without having
the principle of sensuality in them
it would be just the senses
and that again i think probably for
wouldn't want to be qualified for people
as meaning
not just
um because you have like when you say
the senses for example one would think
you have like an image of an eye for
example or in here
but it really means more like the the
senses are there where you are seeing
where you are the the kind of range of
what um
what you can experience through your
senses is what the
senses are
in my understanding
um
so but can you
would you be able to experience anything
through your senses
if
uh the senses
were not
there in the world as in these these
actual flash organs
no existing
no but
um when so then the question is
can you
but can you think then
how do you know you have eyes
as
as something that's necessary for you to
to see
even if it's like you're looking at your
own eyes in the mirror yeah what you see
in the mirror is the result of having
your eyes it's not the eyes yes
so
what is then the eye organ in this case
it is well
the necessary condition for
any site
really that what in in what whatever
there is that is seen
there is um
um
what is like in common to all of that or
behind any of that
is
is what the eye is but it's
but practically from your point of view
where is that eye because obviously now
you're describing it as
the necessary condition and that's all
correct theoretically but practically
the eye that sees while you're
describing to me the eye that sees where
is it what is it
can you think it
can you no because how can you relate i
think so you you will think it yes it's
not can you cannot you will think it but
will the thought
of your eye organ
can it stand for the eye organ or how
can it do so
or can it not do so
so how can you then know it
if you can't even think it
well you can kind of know it by
by realizing that you can't think it in
a way
in in the sense that you can if you if
you are able to distinguish the thought of
are able to distinguish the thought of
the eye
as in saying okay that's a thought that
i have
and even that is that's on the basis of
already that there are sights that
there's um
that i i'm that there's consciousness of
sights as in the things are there
whatever is there
um
that is seen
it's through
through
uh through the eye but
like what's funny is that you do
you know if um if i'm walking in the
forest and there's like a branch that is
uh
you know coming across my path or
something immediately ever you know you
know that if this branch is
is going to
um
cut my eye or something i won't like you
you know that it's a danger to you you
know that it's a problem you know that
you can't see
so then
your thought of about your eyes stands
for your eyes
because why would you then cover your
eye organ
as a result of the thought of your eyes
might be hurt
so it does stand for it so you can't
stand okay so it stands in a way
okay so it stands in a way
you can't um
so what's the problem then i suppose
that's the question
where is the where is the mistake for
somebody who's still not free from
centrality so you can't
so you can't
but not have thoughts if you think about
your organs because that's the only way
to know them
so where is the issue then
because
not free from centrality has thoughts
about his organs and views about his
audience and now seemingly even the one who is
and now seemingly even the one who is
free from sensuality would still have
thoughts about the organs yeah what's
the difference in those thoughts where
is the difference
anyone the assumption uh the assuming
the assumption uh the assuming
how does that manifest
as a difference
um
well with such are you assuming what
the first person has thoughts about the
first person has thoughts about the
organs they're not free from sensuality
another person has the thought about
their sense organs they're free from
centrality what is what is the assumption there
that that thought represents um
an external
yeah or something external to it okay
yeah so
that kind of comes down to
what you put first that's it
so both times you have a thought
in regard to the sense organs but the
first time you put your thought and your
sense of self first
the second instance the one who is free
from centrality recognizes the thought
as a necessary presence
is a necessary way of a organ to be
present but it does not misconceive the
organ to be in the thought
it recognizes that inaccessible
physicality rupa present in during
because of which you are having a
thought of it
but it does not conceive that thought to
be the first or to be inrupa in it or
apart from it or all these permutations
so you understand basically thought for
what it is and it ceases to mis uh
misrepresent the order of things that's it
the order of things that's it
because if you if you don't cease to
misrepresent the order of things then
things can become
mystical overly mystical like in a sense
all right so you know there are these
real senses that i cannot i can think of
but i cannot access but see saying the
real senses
creates another sense uh it's just
another thought
another idea of reality which is again
idea a thought so the point is not to
discover what's behind your thoughts
because this is going to be another
thought the point is to stop putting
that thought
in a wrong place let's say like that
stop assuming it is first in regard to
what you're trying to think
and that's that comes down to
practically that whole uh difference
between the um
i'm not sure we should really get into
that now because you might take us in a
different direction but between like
what's peripherally present while you're
thinking which is another thoughts but
there is a difference in the nature of
thought if it's actually thought and if
it's peripherally enduring
if you assume the external point of view
then yes you can say oh these are all
thoughts but we're not talking about
external point of view without personal
practical point of view whereby you are thinking
point of view whereby you are thinking
something which means other things that
are not directly thought are
peripherally present so seeing the
difference between the two is where you
would undo this wrong order
would that be the difference between
conceiving and thinking
uh well there will be the difference
between uh thinking free from conceiving
and thinking not free from conceiving in
other words thinking
uh results in conceiving or perpetuates
conceiving and then thinking that it's
completely free from conceiving either
ways yeah exactly you can't not have
thoughts and people who believe that you cannot
and people who believe that you cannot
have thoughts and have sort of access to
reality beyond your thoughts are
completely unaware of the blatant
contradiction that that all is another
thought otherwise how can you even refer to
otherwise how can you even refer to
anything outside of your thought unless
you're already thinking it
so the statement becomes contradiction
in terms
i have a friend who's a doctor
and she was saying to me how she finds
it strange how as a doctor
or anybody who studies to become a
doctor like they study the body
very closely and she said i know so well
all i know all the types of diseases
that the body can have
and like i've seen it laid out i've done
you know uh
dissections of
dead human bodies
so how come i don't
see the problem with having a body yeah
and i find that a good example of what you
i find that a good example of what you
just said like the difference between
the peripheral thinking in regard to the
the body as in seeing it as
wherever you go that this body is there
with you yeah basically what happens
with like people observe you can observe
other bodies
but that
that
becomes basically the extension of your
already misconceiving your own senses
because you forget that you cannot
observe your senses in the same sense
you can observe the senses of others now
i can learn about my eyes by you know
observing your eyes and your sense
organs but that does not necessarily imply that
but that does not necessarily imply that
i need to misconceive
mine and you misconceive your organs
when you put the idea the view about it
first and then kind of um assume your
that kind of external position to your
own senses thus by looking at your eyes
yes that's what my eyes are as well but
your eyes can never be seen in that way
so you can
contemplate things externally as the
suitors say
but not losing that peripheral
perspective that your eyes can never be
seen like that so by seeing the external
you know bodies dying or decomposing all
those are super contemplations for
example you then infer that these enduring sense
you then infer that these enduring sense
organs that are peripherally present the
basis for my observation of what i'm
looking at are subjected to the same
nature not the specifics of it
and that's how you get to then undermine
that misconceiving and ownership and
everything else
and that is the the extent of centrality
the extent of sensuality is the
perversion of the order you unpervert
the order there is no more
pursuit of pleasures externally because
it becomes inconceivable
but in order to be able to unperform the
order you have to stop maintaining its
perversion through actions of body speed
to mind
like a person can think all they want
oh i'm i'm not misconceiving my senses
and i'm contemplating saliyatan and so
on but if body speech and mind are not
withdrawn from sensuality and pursuit of
pleasure on account of sense objects
they're perpetuating the perversion of
the order and the misconceiving because
the valuing the pleasures of the sense
valuing the pleasures of the sense
objects is the result of that perversion
so then you can do all the
contemplations you want
if your actions are still perpetuating
the problem you will not upload it
but could you uproot the problem of
centrality simply by being
restrained celibate keeping the precepts
celibate keeping the precepts
why not because it's um
i mean that's a necessary prerequisite
but um it's an assumption um
um it's an assumption um
so you have so say somebody
sticks to it somebody
keeps the precepts
gods of the
gods they sense those
um what just just on its own what would
that result in what could that result in
i mean the strengthening of the mind um and
it is going in in the right direction of
understanding so it's making
understanding so it would still make a
difference yeah for sure
you cannot necessarily well you should
not expect just on its own
to
to undo all the work
but it is part of the work so
obviously just to qualify
just to qualify
if you're keeping the precipitation of
the sensors correctly
as in if you take it on as your practice
that reveals your intentions for which
you feel responsible and weighed under
them not if you take
not if you take
virtue precepts rules as a form of uh or
this is a tradition this is our
authority this is community here does
that so i must do that that's also an
assumption exactly it's like yeah yeah
so in that case in that sense that's
just going to probably make you some
merit by not engaging with sensuality
but it will not bring you a step closer
towards understanding even sensuality
let alone the you know attawad and all
the other assumptions
it needs to be taken personally without
the external
recourse of oh this is the environment
that keeps it for me
so you can you can obviously use the
environment that's supportive for the
precepts they will not bombard you with
sort of
distractions and challenges but you need
to be feeling it on the level of your
intentions and then
and then
even without any
instruction further instruction of
dharma if you're actually doing it on
that level it is even possible to see
the danger and sensuality on your own
simply by abstaining from it but not in
that blind sense i'm holding these
duties religiously because i'm a
buddhist or kazajin said so or was the
community or the tradition or my
upbringing no no because i value
development of mind through kind of
discernment and training in regard to my own
and training in regard to my own
intentions then if you stick to it the
danger will become apparent that's why
an outsider can become free from
sensuality but
but
not again i keep saying that because
people often overlook this and then they
think okay so i'll just keep the
precepts and it's like well yeah but how
do you keep them that's a very relevant
part that is the seal about the paramasa
part that's like the the first three
fetches so
so they need to be they need to be kept
rightly they need to be
felt rightly feel the weight of the
responsibility yeah yeah
so just to
um clarify that was something i was
going to ask you about actually because
yeah it seems to me that you can
you can like you said see the danger and
sensuality just by absolutely um
really keeping to that guarding of
of the senses seeing the senses as
things in themselves or in that do not
need to be acted upon
so therefore you could see the
the extent of the freedom
that could come from not needing to feed
the senses in a way
but that does not necessarily what what
is missing from that in terms of the
buddhist teaching
it doesn't necessarily free you from
atavada because it doesn't imply necessarily
because it doesn't imply necessarily
understanding of
impermanence is that if that is correct yeah yeah
is that if that is correct yeah yeah
yeah
but a person who has say
guided the sense those kept the virtue
correctly discerned through their own intentions
discerned through their own intentions
abandoned the unwholesome one stopped
acting out of them endured them long
enough if they then come across the instruction
if they then come across the instruction
of about a nietzsche it would be
much more self-evident
they will be seed much quicker
so then matavada would appending
whatever will not be as hard as for
somebody who hasn't developed their mind
at all
yeah and i think i as you said and it
makes a lot of sense that
it's almost
in theory though yes exactly exactly
no no because you don't have now back in
the day
you did have presently with the buddha
at the same time teachers who were
teaching the value of abandoning
centrality the patil the danger all of
that so somebody without having heard the
so somebody without having heard the
buddhist teaching could have heard
teaching about the parallel of
centrality took it on faith looked for
things and then seen it because it is
factually perilous
today you won't find teachings outside
of the buddhist sort of dhamma that
would be emphasizing peril of sensuality
and setting you up correctly
you know i did see in other sort of
practices from india like hindu and so
on about you know essentiality is very
unsatisfactory with little benefit
with little benefit
but then how you go about it was just
like well just devote yourself to this
date or that date on this month or that
month like well but you know
anybody can say that
so that's when theoretically yes
somebody can arrive at it
but practically today given that the any
detailed instruction of how to abandon
even sensuality comes from the dharma so
it would be impossible for you to not
know all the other things
that the buddha was teaching so then
so then
that brings us to the next point
uh john
how do you go about it
let's say what what is john
and uh
what would you think a john is how would
you describe it
because it's obviously relevant
to the abandoning of centrality
so how
how is it relevant
do you enter john and then abandon
centrality
or do you abandon sensuality and then
enter john that question yeah
question yeah
it was but i i still want to hear about
china what is young
what's that safety from sensuality
no to safety from
seclusion safety inclusion being
withdrawn from central
so how do you develop that safety
through practicing central strength security security
choosing
you know you're choosing not to
act out of greed hatred delusion what is
a necessary condition
for discernment or pursuit
discernment or pursuit
or value of safety
seeing the danger and safety exactly
you wouldn't be seeking the safety
if you don't think you're in danger
yeah i was going to say because because
to even
like some somebody can ask about this
how can i
achieve this or what is that or why do
you do that
but if that person themselves
is not at least
somewhat dissatisfied already with the
um
pleasures of sensuality or the pl the
kind of pleasure that you can get
in general in the life
um or taking at least not taking it for
granted that life is for enjoying
um
then because
because
then it won't work basically
anything i think we're kind of
presupposing that the person has a
degree of dissatisfaction which is why
they would want to practice jhana
at least correctly in theory but
despite even like people having good
intentions they would go about it in a
wrong way
like they would expect certain practices
to lead to ghana to then in return makes
them not want sensuality anymore and
that's the fundamental problem
you will not discern what janna is i you
will not discern what safety is for as
long as you don't discern the extent of
danger but discerning the extent of danger is
but discerning the extent of danger is
what makes you safe
so
you want to enter jhana you discern the
danger of centrality that is john and
the danger of sensuality
we can talk about it now but before that
that's why like in the suttas
uh the the kind of pleasure and
seclusion of jhana
it's always the result of being
completely withdrawn
withdrawn
um and having it relinquished
basically central desire
craving for pleasure all that so being
withdrawn secluded from unwholesome
states he feels safe and then the
pleasure of that
enduring safety
arises and that you that's what you can
call china
and um
the point i was trying to the point i
wanted to add actually would be that
that so the danger of sensuality
um
[Music] how how would you discern that can i
how how would you discern that can i
tell you just do this do that
breathe like this walk like that sit
like this don't do that
what is the necessary condition
for discerning the danger of centrality
right so the necessary condition
for jhana
is to having had developed an enduring
sense of safety from unwholesome states
of sensuality
necessary condition for developing that
safety is the discernment of the extent of the
is the discernment of the extent of the
danger
what is the necessary condition for
discerning the extent of the danger what
would you practically do in order to
discern the danger how would you go
about it
that's my question
well take a look at how you spend your
time 24 hours a day and how much the
value of sensuality determines your
actions yeah and say
yeah and say
you have done that
and you have recognized number of times
that you still
go towards sensuality choose towards
centrality as we said many times before
essentially it doesn't happen by
accident you always choose it welcome it
enlightened attacked out of it
so you have recognized some extent so
what do you do then how do you deal with
that what can you do once you recognize that
what can you do once you recognize that
yes i am engaging with
sensuality on some level and still value
it how do you abandon that
is it discerning the gratification in
sensuality yeah yeah
so
how would you do that
what do you what questions you need to
ask what do you look for
are we already assuming that somebody is
you know not
um acting on yeah well basically we are
talking about us let's say that yeah so
what i mean is like to what extent you
know if um let's say you're in in
seclusion um
um
or is it you know i'm i'm already
throughout my day i'm seeing
is it on the level of one is saying oh
like here um
throughout my day my actions are to some
extent uh guided by the
acting out of unwholesome or is it
um that you are
seeing that you are already choosing to
not act
out of unwholesome in any way
well either way you can choose to not
act but the mind still values sexuality
so you still haven't seen the danger
so the question is then how do you see
the danger
like that's the only reason you're still
valuing centuries you might not act out
of it you might not be choosing it
but if you
but you're still not free from it
why is that because the danger hasn't
been fully understood why is that
so in other words can you
think that you are completely not using it
that you are completely not using it
anymore completely not acting anymore
and still not see the danger no you
can't exactly exactly exactly so the
point then comes when you think yes you
i'm restrained i'm not acting yet i'm
not seeing sensuality well that's
impossible yeah
yeah
if the sensuality the dangerous
sexuality is not seen means on some
level you're still welcoming the
lighting and perpetuating it you know
and that's then okay so that's what you
need to look for and see the connection
between the two
try to see what is dangerous that you
have to reflect on why is this dangerous
uh yeah
well basically any any approach any
provider whether it's through
gratification like
why is this pleasure so valuable to me
what is the the gratifying aspect
of this delight of this of this desire
or yes on some other occasion what is
the dangerous aspect of engaging with it
either way the point is to not engage
with it and to learn how to not welcome
it so the danger becomes apparent
because the danger is there
and that's how you get the john
like you wouldn't be able to do these
reflections and and pursue this questioning that
and and pursue this questioning that
will bring the discernment of what you
are actually doing on the level of your
mind in terms of welcoming sensuality or
not and so on
unless you have been thoroughly
restrained guiding of the sense those
and spending your time in seclusion and
non-distraction with the external world
but you will certainly not be able to
see any of this if you expect these
answers to come magically or even worse
if you expect that end result of jhana
which is that kind of pleasure of that
safety that has been enduring for a
while to come as a result of like
physical observations of sensations or
so the questioning of sensuality
discernment of the domain the extent the
danger the gratification is how you get
done is how you withdraw yourself from the
is how you withdraw yourself from the
unwholesome states and that's why in the
suit as they're like and many different
ways of
inquiry contemplation
would be the basis for jhana
in other words thinking and pondering
thinking and pondering on account of
dead bodies thinking and pondering
as well thinking and pondering on
account of
other aspects of dharma
usually translated as meditations but
you realize no it was just the lines of
questioning and discernment done rightly
can then become the basis for safety i
based it for the first genre
and i think i saw the ones in the like
uh
what was it you know ponika i think did
this it was just a list compilation on
the basis of sort of what's mentioned in
the suit is like a very commentarial
style and it was like all these
contemplations and practices that were
mentioned the suit is they can serve as
a basis for first it can be become a
first genre but it has to be on the
right level well that's what you realize
you know initially also if i do this
john no no on account of any of these
lines of inquiry and discernment if
you're doing them rightly because they
will result if you're doing them rightly
they will result in safety from
sensuality because the danger would have become
because the danger would have become
apparent and that then results in
complete sort of seclusion from
unwholesome states that you become
self-aware of
and that's the jhana
and that's why like in the suttas when
the monks were saying oh i you know i
can obtain ghanas at will and so on
it wasn't because they had this this you
know tapped into some mystical plane
that they have always contact with no
it's because they recognize that by
protecting the uh
the uh
the lifestyle
of seclusion
guarding of the sentence those virtue
perception of danger
john is perpetually accessible
and he was exactly there oh no no that's
why i live in these rough forests
because jhanas are accessible to me at
any given time and that's why jannas are
accessible to me at every given time
because i live with drone in these rough
forests
so chana is the result of right
withdrawal from unwholesome things
that's sort of followed by discernment
which obviously johnny's safety yeah the
unhealthy that's that was the definition
sure safety from the unwholesome
is also the
knowledge of the danger
of
yes as long as again
knowledge of the danger got to be the
real knowledge or the danger in a sense
because um inevitably when somebody practically
um inevitably when somebody practically
does begin to contemplate the danger it
will be on the level of theoretical
knowledge of the danger with some kind
of
personal you could relate to it
personally to some extent but the danger
really needs to be felt the danger of if
i welcome this engage with this the the
the possibility of
that just direction going in that
direction of welcoming centrality or of
central pleasure that's already the
peril so so
but then
what would be or you mentioned
gratification and so another as i said
another way of discerning what the
danger is is to recognize what
gratification is
so what is the gratifying aspects of
centrality it's delighting in the possibility of
it's delighting in the possibility of
getting rid of
the pain of one's presently enduring
experiences so
are you saying then that delight is the
problem and uh seeing hearing smelling tasting
and uh seeing hearing smelling tasting
touching the sense object of pleasure is
not a problem
yeah so um
the pleasure isn't again the touch yeah
you said yes yeah
so
can you engage with sight sound smell
this touch of the pleasure pleasurable
kind without the delight in it
yeah
blanket blanket yes always you can
always engage with it
or other certain smell taste touches
that always imply the light oh yeah
things like uh sexuality and exactly
things that are against the presets
always imply delight
always imply perversion of that order
yeah but yes
once you say no to those things then
some engagement with sense objects
whether they're agreeably secure or
present or not can sometimes be
agreeable sometimes not which means you
could uh remove the delight from those things
uh remove the delight from those things
so what is the delight then
what is the delight
it's it's on the level of the
possibility in the sense that
yeah you could experience but
practically practically
if i'm not thinking about possibilities
if if those are things a bit too subtle
for me
practically where is this delight that i
obviously have because i obviously
pursue sensuality saving wanting more so
wanting more pleasure wanting to get rid
of the pain i to get rid of the pain
ultimately yeah so then the the wanting
of it
uh
again you know i might not think in
terms of getting rid of the pain
you just feel the pressure the pull
the the intensity of central desire yeah
and then you give in to it
what is the delight
the possibility of getting rid of that
pain no but where is it my delight see
no but where is it my delight see
possibilities arise as part of things
delight doesn't if the light were truly
the possibility you wouldn't be able to
free yourself from it
so yes there are possibilities of
getting rid of it but i am the one
delighting there is something you are perpetuating
so how do you not perpetuate your
delight in sensuality anymore
i'm not choosing
choosing not to do that
if i'm the one delighting
can you just choose to not delight
because you're already
you know undermined by the light you
don't start with a neutral position
where the light comes and then you choose
the light comes and then you choose
enough maybe you know somebody has been
practicing longer can see it coming before it comes
longer can see it coming before it comes
but
somebody is not free from sensuality are
always undermined by their delight
so in other words you cannot not delight
by choice immediately certainly but how
do you start uprooting it so it can
become a choice
yes sir um allowing
allowing
what yeah i mean obviously virtually
incentive straight so allowing
the um
this discomfort to endure exactly
without it exactly
that will basically see
delight is always exactly as you said before
is always exactly as you said before
exemplify through this possibility of
dealing with the discomfort dealing so
by welcoming it welcoming that
possibility you are delighting
and you will do that inevitably you
can't just say no to that but what you
don't have to do is follow up on that
delight so you welcome the possibility
so you welcome the possibility
to get rid of the unpleasant itch
and get pleasure as a result of it
mind is elated at the possibility of it
and you endure that now
and that is much harder and it becomes
obviously much more refined
than just
saying no to things
right kind of on the base level and
trying to prevent them from even arising
yeah oh this massive no no that's the kind of
oh this massive no no that's the kind of
whole point yes you say no to base
things such as things that are against
the precepts
things will start arising the light will
start happening you don't want to get
rid of it you want to be able to endure
it without acting out of it so in other
words people
still delight because they don't see the
extent of the delight
that's it
by seeing the extent of the delight
and enduring it's efficiently enough
you'll stop delighting in it
and then the gratification is understood
then the danger is understood and then
the escape isn't instilled escape is not
pulling your eyes out or never seeing
anything agreeable that there was lust
provoking like before the danger is
being unable
to accept the prospect of the light to
delight in it
why could you understood the danger
so the danger is of the delight on the
level of
mental attitude of delight that's the
pedal that's the the by the biting of
debate that then you're controlled by
not the actual beautiful things in the
world that are agreeable and people lust
for but yes in order to get there first you
but yes in order to get there first you
need to say no to those things to engage
with those things but then you need to
take it on that internal level and it's
much sharper there
then if our practice is to just sort of
adhere and protect and control the
circumstances so that nothing even
arises nothing even crosses my field of
vision it's like yeah you don't seek it
out but inevitably things will
but inevitably things will
uh provoke lust and delight in your mind
so what do you do then you try to negate
it deny it cover it up get rid of it or
actually learn how to endure it to its
full extent without acting out and
that's why people are afraid to endure
it
because they're doubtful whether they're
lacked out or not
and you don't want to do it because you
might act out and then wait is even more
i might act out and undermine everything
i work for yeah exactly that's the
danger that's the pedal you enjoy it
long enough it will become apparent but
if you don't want to let it endure in
that sense and just double down and
redefine the rule and introduce more
also this never ever happens just like
you're fighting the problem on a wrong
wrong place
you're not saying that it's a risen by
itself um so
you're not able to see the extent
because you're trying to put yourself
well yeah you're not able to see the
extent because you're unable to endure
its extent
like you can see and not see and stuff
but if you're able to endure it without
acting out
abs off of it doesn't matter how refined it
off of it doesn't matter how refined it
gets
endure it
it will be seen the delight like and you
you're already delighting as i said yeah
it's already welcomed yeah yeah okay i
already welcome this how do you stop it
no see now you're trying to stop it and
everything to get rid of what you
already welcome no you need to endure
what you already welcome to see the
mistake of welcoming it
not to cover it up and that's the
difference
so you mentioned these contemplations um
for example like asuba
um
and yeah like
yeah like
one interpretation of a subaru is
yeah the like the the ugly
yeah you contemplate the ugly like um
as a means of replacing
sensuality yeah that's the problem yeah rather than
yeah that's the problem yeah rather than
seeing sensuality is ugly exactly that's
where you you're trying to to paste over
the view the idea of ugly ugly ugly ugly
ugly to kind of push away the
unpleasantness of having to endure the
delighted sensuality
instead the true super practice is on
the level of if you have endured it
already sufficiently enough you get to
see the ugly in it and then the
endurance becomes pleasant yeah
becomes equated with freedom
renunciation yeah
but if you're doing it in response to
not wanting to endure it because it's
unpleasant then it's just a cover-up
yeah then it's not done rightly
then the wrong order still remains
unchanged so all of these contemplations
they require this yes
as i say often that that kind of right
endurance is the basis for any dharma
approach to apply
same with like annapurna
but the lies in the different
different
foods of the different senses to put it
like that in like the if the senses are
like these um the six hungry animals
like this in that
simile then i
i
i find it a good image because
it really is like that that these senses
are just kind of dragging you and
pulling you in the different directions
and the
reason that you keep following them or
kind of running after them
that's kind of um in a way the delight
like when you delight in something that
the senses are kind of um
dragging you towards
going towards it with them you don't
feel like you're being dragged
so it's like that's the only feeling of
kind of relief or peace or you're kind
of stimulating the feeling of relief or
peace by kind of following after them
um so that you don't see that it's
actually them dragging you not you so
you don't want to endure the discomfort
of being dragged see if you stop
resisting being dragged around if you
start running with it
the tension will disappear
the dog is yanking you
and you try to fight it and then you get
all this all this tension and pain and
you have to fight it for who knows how
long but if you just start running with it
but if you just start running with it
yeah oh you don't feel the tension
anymore but you realize but yeah now i
have to run i have to keep moving yeah
all the time all the time
and that's exactly why
people would delight because they don't
want to go through discomfort
of
already hungry wild untamed senses
so as i said before you have an option
you can yes keep enabling the wild
animal so it doesn't harass you or you
can endure the harassment so the animal
will come down and you can finally train
it and then you don't need to run nor do
you need to fight the detention
but for somebody who's already that's
the thing that's why you have to start
with the stop with stopping firstly yeah
you got to stand your ground and just
hold on to dilation because otherwise
you don't even realize that that's the
that's the similarity wasn't it the uh
taming of the elephant like you don't
bring the wild elephant and immediately
start issuing instructions to it
expecting it to obey no well yeah then
you strap it down to a strong post tie
down and
it will be kicking screaming urinating
defecating going mental
but it will have to come down because it
it will have to come down because it
will tire itself out
and if you don't let it run away if you
don't sort of unhook it
it will come down and then
you know it will start taking food and
then we start listening to you and so
you broke it down
broke it in
and that's uh that's exactly the the
training like uh
like uh
you can do it you know some people
can do it more gradually somewhere but
the point is yeah you got to start
containing yourself
from spilling outwards
so that then the mind will learn how to
calm down within that
because for as long as there is a
possibility for it to go out and relieve
itself from you know
things that are kind of confining then
uh it will seek it
only when it renounces that when the
senses realize no it just it's not going
there it hasn't been going there for a
while this is the way we say the virtue
has been developed beforehand
it's a it's a necessity prerequisite
but it is uh counter-intuitive at first
because because engaging in sensuality
does get rid of
get rid of
craving temporary like the dog is
screaming and barking and restless and
ripping your apartment up
because it wants food so you give it
food and it will stop
but see now next time we'll do that
again when he wants your food it will
cause you damage if you don't give it
food it's like actually yes i could
appease it and get a temporary relief
but as a result of it i am perpetuating
that habit that it's undermining me
further and making things worse and
worse so that's exactly your senses yeah
so that's exactly your senses yeah
that's the five senses exactly
and it's really only by you know if you
first stop it's only then that you
realize how wild the animal is yeah
that's the only reason i delight is
because you will not even recognize the
strength of the pool until you stop why
because you've been running with it but
when you stop then you realize the
weight is against the grain yeah yeah yeah and
is against the grain yeah yeah yeah and
that's also
like the
way i think to
understand the difference between like
the principle of sensuality as or how i
put it and
let's say it's not about just just like
specific types of objects for example
yeah it's really the principle of that
being pulled sure
and i think it's important to maybe
i think it's important to maybe
emphasize that yeah in the broader sense
you start with a specific object
specific acts that said that always
imply delight and so on but yeah that's
just so to contain yourself so that that
you realize that the light is what
colors the picture
called someone wholesome
so then i guess the next point would be
danger to kind of cover the gratification
to kind of cover the gratification
what is the
what is the danger aspect practically
acutely what is the danger in the light
what is the danger in the light
so presence of the light means danger
why
you're inserting yourself um
but you know things remain impermanent
either way
why is it dangerous for me
that impermanence
because um
you're perpetuating this assumption of
being able to control your feelings
which is a false assumption and so
um
you're making yourself liable to
hearty and permanence of female that's
the point how am i making myself liable
where is that
liability that i'm responsible for so
that this
delight is dangerous
making me making me susceptible to
danger in that assumption
in that assumption
of which one
of sensuality
but no the assumption is because of the
delight because when you delight as in you
because when you delight as in you
follow after one of these wild animals you
you
kind of you can't make yourself part you
you become the sense in a way you are
you assume this
yes you take on the ownership whether you
you take on the ownership whether you
want it or not so you are taking on that
ownership therefore
it's you so would you be taking the
ownership even if you don't follow that animal
even if you don't follow that animal
but the delight is there you're already
delighted but you're not following you are
but you're not following you are
restrained
would that be implying the ownership
so you don't go all the way
off following become dependent on
pleasure but the delight is there so if
the delight is there is the ownership
there
or it takes time for the ownership to
develop it takes time for the ownership to
it takes time for the ownership to
deliver no no this is
this is
you can see in terms of the
five holding aggregates which is what sakaya
holding aggregates which is what sakaya
is
and um you know is that holding separate
or not now it's the delight and lust
i would say for the six senses it's
basically the same yeah yeah so presence
of delight is presence of danger because
presence of delight is presence of
ownership of that which which you cannot own
of that which which you cannot own
okay yeah yeah of course yeah so is it
then valid for someone who has following
our discussion so far
to start making
at least in their thinking and click or
distinction between let's say me here
and six senses which are about animals
doing their own thing and i want to keep
as separate from that as possible
not not projecting myself into
those senses
no no it's not on the level of
projection first what person would need to do is
first what person would need to do is
recognize that if they think about the
senses separate from them the six
animals or them separate from the senses
that's already the result of the six
animals so first they need to find the practical
so first they need to find the practical
examples of the six animals pulling them
they're delighting in the aspect of
relief and then discern
and then discern
them
themselves on that level
yeah so bad in other words if you want
to contemplate yourself separate from
the animals you do that
on the basis of the animal pull
pressure pain you have to endure
yes so you're going to see yourself in
that sense whether the light
with those senses
yeah well that's what i'm saying that's
where your sense of self is exactly like
you might not see yourself there if you
expect to see yourself elsewhere or in
different terms so you gotta abandon
your expectations of where myself is
and start enduring things on the right
level and then
again make the effort to basically
prevent yourself from interpreting
yourself in these external terms
and actually see that i might not see it
now i might see it later but if i
understand this correctly my sense of
ownership i my sense of self is here on
this level of basically pressure of the
senses that i don't want to endure that
i delight to get rid of
that's where it is
so
i don't think you could just
extrapolate the contemplation of the
self separate from the senses and do it
independent of
the practical basis of the endurance of
the five animals no that's kind of the
point yeah yeah because the starting
point will be that there is already
identification with the sense exactly
exactly just decide to step out of the
whole thing
yeah so the closest you can come to
discerning um um
the
the holding off assumption of self is by
discerning what you have just said the
delight in the domain of the census yeah
so then practically the closest you
could come to discerning the not-self
is to enduring the pull of the animals
without covering it up without giving in
without justifying it trying to get rid
of it without managing it psychologizing
it
because that is that which will truly
reveal to you how much you don't own
your own senses your own self
how much
how wild they are and you like you don't
even exist for them yeah a wild dog you
are just a feature in the world like it
doesn't care for you doesn't respect you
doesn't listen to you that's for sure
so but people do see by constantly
acting out and running out with these
animals so they don't feel the tension
they develop this oh yeah this is i am
this is mine
uh my senses obey me because look i can
send them here i can send them there i
can pull them to run to the left but you
can't stop because if you stop they will
rip you apart
also you're very much just their servant
a convenient servant yes they need you
for directing like five uh five organs
five sense organs need the mind
they meet in it they get a sense from it
they get the meaning from it the the
whole possibilities
but in reality it's like which one comes
first which one is subjugated to the
other one which one is the servant
is the mind the servant of the five
senses or has the mind developed so the
five senses are are basically
subordinates to the mind
and yes for most people the mind is the
servant of the senses
through and through
although the mind maintains this this
arrogant assumption that this is mine i
am in charge because look i can turn
left i can turn right
yeah can you stop it but
once the sensors have calmed down you've
endured the pressure long enough
they've calmed down then what is
revealed is who now is the master yeah
is who now is the master yeah
the unknown ability you realize oh these
i cannot be these animals because if i
were they would be in my control but yet
look at him
kicking a scream so i can only tame them
i can only calm them down but i cannot
be them they cannot be mine
and so one can discern the senses
already being present already hunting
and chasing things
and secondly it's not just one sense
doing that it's actually five
simultaneously yeah
yeah yeah so
then um
um
that already undercuts the idea of there
being one owner yeah because it's like
walking with five or six different
animals on a leash going in all
directions so where do you think you're
going with all that and the problem for
people is because if you've been running
with them so you don't experience the
pain and the pressure in the pool
you stop seeing them all you see is
yourself running
so people don't even see the five senses
for what they are
and that's exactly that uh identifying
aspect that gets developed on account of that
that gets developed on account of that
assumed ownership like you think you are
it you think you are what you see here
is melted you think you are those senses
so you put those views those ideas first
as we started in the beginning as you
said that
failing to realize no they they are
actually physical organ of eyes nose
the five senses
that i cannot be identified with even if
i want to because they are endured there
in the world subjected to elements and
everything else so that contemplation
can be enough to make get you started so
to speak so you you don't identify as
much but fundamentally it's going to
boil down whether you're still acting
towards it or not whether you're able to
endure the delight for as far as it goes
as sharp as it gets that but only if i
touch this the relief will happen just
just this tiny no
because it would be done for the wrong
reason out of that perversion
if that's if the light is not there
that's fine then things are not an issue
if the light is is not present if you
have uprooted it but until that happens
you have to recognize that the danger
is not in everything else that would
follow on a kind of a gadget yes it is
but the more acute danger of sensuality
is on the level of presence of delight
means ownership is already there means wild
ownership is already there means wild
animals are in charge at least to that
extent and if you were to recognize truly that
and if you were to recognize truly that
even like a second of that perversion of
the order implies the danger of the
entire domain you you missed everything
else possible yeah yes oh no this is it
it doesn't matter oh well it's not as
much as before yeah that's good but just
the grain of it is equally bad
a grain of delight and this is why a
non-disciple noble disciple can make
progress in dharma by developing the
perception of non-delight in the entire
world in the entire world yeah yeah yeah
and the would have said similarly in
regard to
being isn't it like even the small
traces of it it's like the excrement
whether it's a you know a bucket of it
or a tiny smell it smells the same it's
horrible and so it's a being
and so it's a being
any being so whether it's karma baba or
just like being of sensuality or just being
like being of sensuality or just being
clear from centrality either way
tiny bit of being
it's as bad as a lot of being
it has the same smell the same danger
the same pedal
like you said that
i find that important to not to forget
that the senses are these physical
things in the world that uh are
in the world that uh are
just made of matter subjected to
elements and that's exactly sorry like
because we mentioned peripheral in the
beginning yes see you find very
important to not forget that and you
realize okay so it's a it's a type of
reminding yourself
through certain contexts and
contemplations and that's how you
practice that peripheral awareness
because you cannot directly perceive
those senses but by reminding of the
right order as in they do have to be in
the world they're independent
or not identified with like in order i
can identify with the senses and forget
about them is because they're already
there so if you never forget that that's how
so if you never forget that that's how
you practice the peripheral awareness
that we spoke about in our previous
videos not by some method of you know
looking peripherally no reminding
yourself of the context that that's
based on the right order
and that's that is why it's helpful okay
so just
keep that and you can never spill out of
it you know you can forget you can get
distracted within it
until you work on that aspect of things
but fundamentally that will be your kind
of outer wall
these senses i cannot go outside of i
cannot spill outside i am within them i
am containing them they are my ways of
accessing the world
yeah and so therefore that even makes
the the danger of ownership of them even
the danger of ownership of them even
worse in a way because not only are you
this constant slave of them
but bound for destruction and you're going
bound for destruction and you're going
that way if you don't abandon them yeah
and that becomes your destruction yeah
exactly yeah yeah you would well the
dogs are running down the cliff so
unless you learn how to completely
detach yourself from from the five
strands of central pleasures you will be
flying down their cliff as well